{
  "reference_number": "1830",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Physics doesn't negotiate with different gas types. They all cause warming, they must all come down to net zero."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Overseas carbon credit schemes have long proven to be not good enough."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but only revising the target to below net zero, or bringing the net zero date forward to sooner than 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes, but the budget should ONLY be able to be altered down, to be more ambitious in emissions reductions. This has to be a race to\n the top in ambition, not a race to the bottom. No government should be able to weaken the ambition of a previous government."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but the budget should ONLY be able to be altered down, to be more ambitious in emissions reductions. This has to be a race to\n the top in ambition, not a race to the bottom. No government should be able to weaken the ambition of a previous government."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate Change is a global problem – it cannot be tackled by countries in isolation. New Zealand must demonstrate global leadership\nand match its bold domestic emissions reduction agenda: by having an equally ambitious climate change strategy abroad. Access to\n\nclimate finance is a matter of climate justice – those who have contributed least to the causes of climate change are typically the\nmost vulnerable to its impacts and have the least resources to respond. We must take responsibility for our global emissions and the\n\nclimate impacts that we have contributed to. It’s very important that all New Zealanders have their say on how we make the shift to a\nzero carbon future here in New Zealand but we must also help the world’s most vulnerable communities across the Pacific adjust to\n\nthe impacts on climate change. We must ensure that the Zero Carbon Bill is transparent. This means the bill must include a\nrequirement to produce annual reports about New Zealand’s international climate change contributions in order to ensure that the\nPacific countries get the support they need and can plan to adapt to their changing environment. Transparency in the Bill will promote\n\npublic engagement and political accountability. New Zealanders will be able to understand the international contributions we are\nmaking and as a nation, we will be able to stand tall that we are supporting our Pacific neighbours adapt to their climate change reality.\n\nNew Zealand has demonstrated global leadership with our commitment to stopping oil and gas exploration – now let us continue that\nmoral leadership and include transparency in what and how we support climate change efforts abroad, particularly in the Pacific."
    }
  ]
}
